<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE VARIANTS [
	<!ELEMENT VARIANTS (DESCRIPTION, MAP_DEFINITION+, VARIANT+)>
	
	<!ELEMENT DESCRIPTION (#PCDATA)>
	
	<!ELEMENT MAP_DEFINITION (DESCRIPTION?)>
	<!ATTLIST MAP_DEFINITION 
		id ID #REQUIRED
		title CDATA #REQUIRED
		URI CDATA #REQUIRED
		thumbURI CDATA #REQUIRED
		preferredUnitStyle CDATA #IMPLIED
		>
	
	<!ELEMENT VARIANT (DESCRIPTION, MAP, RULEOPTIONS?, POWER+, STARTINGTIME, VICTORYCONDITIONS, SUPPLYCENTER+, INITIALSTATE*)>
	<!ATTLIST VARIANT
			name CDATA #REQUIRED
			default (true|false) "false"
			version CDATA #REQUIRED
			aliases CDATA #IMPLIED
			>
			
	<!ELEMENT MAP (MAP_GRAPHIC*)>
	<!ATTLIST MAP adjacencyURI CDATA #REQUIRED>
	
	<!ELEMENT MAP_GRAPHIC EMPTY>
	<!ATTLIST MAP_GRAPHIC
			ref IDREF #REQUIRED
			default (true|false) "false"
			preferredUnitStyle CDATA #IMPLIED
			>
	
	<!ELEMENT RULEOPTIONS (RULEOPTION+)>
	<!ELEMENT RULEOPTION EMPTY>
	<!ATTLIST RULEOPTION	name CDATA #REQUIRED
				value CDATA #REQUIRED>
	
	<!ELEMENT POWER EMPTY>
	<!ATTLIST POWER name CDATA #REQUIRED
			active (true|false) "true"
			adjective CDATA #REQUIRED
			altnames CDATA #IMPLIED
			>
	
	<!ELEMENT STARTINGTIME EMPTY>
	<!ATTLIST STARTINGTIME 	turn CDATA #REQUIRED
				allowBCYears (true|false) "false"
				>
	
	<!ELEMENT VICTORYCONDITIONS (WINNING_SUPPLY_CENTERS?, YEARS_WITHOUT_SC_CAPTURE?, GAME_LENGTH?)>
	
	<!ELEMENT WINNING_SUPPLY_CENTERS EMPTY>
	<!ATTLIST WINNING_SUPPLY_CENTERS value CDATA #REQUIRED>
	
	<!ELEMENT YEARS_WITHOUT_SC_CAPTURE EMPTY>
	<!ATTLIST YEARS_WITHOUT_SC_CAPTURE value CDATA #REQUIRED>
	
	<!ELEMENT GAME_LENGTH EMPTY>
	<!ATTLIST GAME_LENGTH value CDATA #REQUIRED>
	
	<!ELEMENT SUPPLYCENTER EMPTY>
	<!ATTLIST SUPPLYCENTER 	province CDATA #REQUIRED
				homepower CDATA "none"
				owner CDATA "none"
				>
				
	<!ELEMENT INITIALSTATE EMPTY>
	<!ATTLIST INITIALSTATE 	province CDATA #REQUIRED
				power CDATA #REQUIRED
				unit CDATA #REQUIRED
				unitcoast CDATA #IMPLIED
				>
]>
<VARIANTS>
	<DESCRIPTION><![CDATA[Ancient Mediterranean variant.]]></DESCRIPTION>
	
	<MAP_DEFINITION id="ancientmed" title="Ancient Mediterranean"
		URI="ancientmed.svg" thumbURI="ancientmed_thumb.jpg" preferredUnitStyle="Ancient Mediterranean">
		<DESCRIPTION>
		The map for Ancient Med variant.
		</DESCRIPTION>
	</MAP_DEFINITION>
	
	<VARIANT name="Ancient Mediterranean" version="1.0" aliases="ancientmed">
		<DESCRIPTION><![CDATA[
		<p>
			The Ancient Mediterranean is a five-player Diplomacy variant based on the empires
			that dominated the Mediterranean area during ancient history.
		</p>
			The powers are Rome, Carthage, Greece, Egypt and Persia. Much emphasis has been
			placed on the playability of the variant. As for its historical accuracy, the game
			depicts a period of history which is quite broad - not a single point in time.
		</p>
		<p>
			The rules are consistent with the normal rules of Diplomacy, with some minor
			exceptions due to the geography of the area.
		</p>
		<h2>Rules for Ancient Mediterranean</h2>
		<p>
			The normal rules of the game of Diplomacy apply, with the following additions,
			exceptions and clarifications.
		</p>
		<h2>Home Supply Centers and Starting Positions</h2>
		<p>
			<b>Rome</b>    (red):         fleet Neapolis,     army Roma,      army Ravenna<br>
			<b>Carthage</b> (blue):        fleet Thapsus,      army Cirta,     army Carthage<br>
			<b>Greece</b>   (green):       fleet Sparta,       army Athens,   army Macedonia<br>
			<b>Persia</b>   (black):       fleet Sidon,        army Antioch,   army Damascus<br>
			<b>Egypt</b>    (yellow):      fleet Alexandria,   army Memphis,   army Thebes<br>
		</p>
		<h2>Victory criteria</h2>
		<p>
			18 supply centers.
		</p>
		<h2>Move dates and adjustments</h2>
		<p>
			As in the normal rules, each turn alternates between Spring and Fall, starting
			the game on a Spring turn, with adjustments being made after a Fall turn. Each
			successive Spring the year increases by one. The gameÕs first year is 01 AD.
		</p>
		<h2>Impassable spaces</h2>
		<p>
			Any areas that are not named on the board are not passable. The Atlantic Ocean
			can not be occupied by any units.
		</p>
		<h2>Islands</h2>
		<p>
			Islands are distinct spaces. An island may be occupied by an army or a fleet.
			Each island has one continuous coast, therefore a fleet on an island may move
			to any space adjacent to it. For example, a fleet could move from the Egyptian
			Sea to Crete in one turn, and then move to the Aegean Sea in the next turn.
		</p>
		<h2>Movement across narrow straits</h2>
		<p>
			Arrows on the board indicate two adjacent land spaces. An army may move from one
			space to the other in one turn without being convoyed. Because they are adjacent,
			fleets may also move from one space to the other in one turn.
		</p>
		<h2>Byzantium</h2>
		<p>
			Byzantium is one space which straddles a waterway. The waterway allows movement
			of a fleet in Byzantium to any adjacent coastal space or sea space. The waterway
			does not impede the movement of an army through Byzantium. And it is a supply center.
			In other words, it works just like Constantinople in the standard game.
		</p>
		<h2>Baleares</h2>
		<p>
			Baleares is a single space which consists of the islands and the water around them.
			Since it contains both land and water, it can be occupied by a fleet or an army.
			However, it is still considered one single space and can only be occupied by one unit
			at a time. Although an army can occupy Baleares, it can not move there directly from
			the mainland spaces since the islands are too far from the coast. For an army to enter
			or leave Baleares, it would have to be convoyed by a fleet in the Berber Sea or the
			Ligurian Sea. Since Baleares consists mostly of water, it is considered a sea space for
			the purposes of convoys, therefore a fleet occupying Baleares may be used to convoy an
			army using the normal convoy rules. Baleares is a supply center.
		</p>
		<h2>Four-way intersection in the high seas</h2>
		<p>
			In the middle of the board there is an area where four sea spaces come together at one
			point. They are the Ausonian Sea, Messenian Sea, Gulf of Tacape and Libyan Sea. All four
			of these spaces are adjacent to each of the other three at that point. Therefore, a fleet
			in one of these spaces may move to any of the other three.
		</p>
		<p>
			Also, by virtue of the expanse of the open seas, fleets can pass each other in a criss-cross
			fashion without impeding each others' movement. For example, a Roman fleet could move from
			the Ausonian Sea to the Libyan Sea and a Greek fleet could move from the Messenian Sea to the
			Gulf of Tacape on the same turn and both of these moves would be allowed. Note that this
			criss-crossing is not the same as two units exchanging places. For example, if a Roman fleet
			tried to move from the Ausonian Sea to the Libyan Sea and an Egyptian fleet tried to move from
			the Libyan Sea to the Ausonian Sea on the same turn, these moves would not be allowed due to
			the normal rules.
		</p>
		<h2>The Diolkos</h2>
		<p>
			The border between Sparta and Athens effectively works like a canal. It cuts across the isthmus
			and allows fleets to move through. For example, a fleet in the Aegean Sea could move to Athens
			and then, on the following turn, to the Ionian Sea. Note that in game terms, this means Athens
			effectively has one continuous coast. Armies can freely move between Sparta and Athens.
		</p>
		<p>
			The historical precedence for this is not an actual canal. The Diolkos was a roadway built by the
			Greeks for the purpose of moving ships across the isthmus.
		</p>
		<h2>The Nile river and canal</h2>
		<p>
			The Nile River acts as the boundary between the spaces on its east and west banks. The river is
			not a space on the board. It can not be occupied by any units. However, it is considered to be
			navigable. Therefore, a fleet may move between spaces that are adjacent along the river. For
			example, Sinai to Thebes, Thebes to Memphis, Memphis to Alexandria would all be legal moves for a
			fleet. Memphis to Cyrene would not be a legal move for a fleet. Egypt can build fleets in any of
			its home supply centers.
		</p>
		<p>
			There is also a canal that connects the Nile River to the Reed Sea. It acts as the boundary between
			Sinai and Thebes. It is also navigable and therefore allows fleet movement between Sinai, Thebes
			and Reed Sea. Reed Sea is not adjacent to the Gulf of Pelusium or Alexandria. Notice that due to the
			various waterways and coasts that Sinai and Thebes each have one continuous coast.
		</p>
			Armies can freely move across the Nile River and canal.
		<p>
			There actually is much precedence for a canal connecting the Nile River to the Red Sea in ancient history.
		</p>
		<h2>The Nile river delta</h2>
		<p>
			The Nile River Delta is not a distinct space on the board. It can not be occupied by any units. There are
			four spaces which are in contact with the delta. They are Alexandria, Thebes, Sinai and the Gulf of Pelusium.
			All four of these spaces are considered to be adjacent to each of the other three, at all times, by virtue
			of the multiple water channels in the delta. This provides increased flexibility concerning the movement of
			fleets. A fleet in any of these four spaces may move to any of the other three. The delta does not impede the
			movement of armies. An army in any of the three land spaces in contact with the delta, may move to either of
			the other two.
		</p>
		<p>
			The key to remember is that Thebes is always adjacent to the Gulf of Pelusium AND Alexandria is always adjacent
			to Sinai (in addition to the obvious adjacancies). For example, a fleet could move from Thebes to the Gulf of
			Pelusium and, on the same turn, an army or a fleet, could move from Alexandria to Sinai.
		</p>
		<h2>Convoy clarifications</h2>
		<p>
			As in the normal rules, no fleet in a land space can convoy armies. This includes any coastal space, island,
			Byzantium and land spaces adjacent to the Nile River or the delta. Baleares is considered primarily a sea
			space for the purposes of convoys, therefore a fleet occupying it may be used to convoy an army using the
			normal convoy rules.
		</p>
		<h2>Abbreviations for Ancient Mediterranean names</h2>
		<p>
			For almost every space on the board, the first three letters of the name are used for its abbreviation.
			This includes spaces which have two words in the name. So the Egyptian Sea is Egy and the <i>Cilician Strait</i>
			is <i>CIL</i>. None of the letters in the words "sea" or "strait" are used. However, names that have three words
			in them use the first letter of each of the three words. So the Gulf of Pelusium is GoP. There are only a few
			exceptions to these guidelines due to redundancies. The following is a complete list of the exceptions to the
			"use the first three letters" rule.
		</p>
		<p style="margin-left:1cm;">
			Gulf of Pelusium   <b>GoP</b><br>
			Gulf of Syrtis     <b>GoS</b><br>
			Gulf of Tacape     <b>GoT</b><br>
			Sardinia           <b>Sad</b><br>
			Sarmatia           <b>Sam</b><br>
			Sinai              <b>Sii</b><br>
			Sinope             <b>Sip</b><br>
			Tyre               <b>Tye</b><br>
			Tyrrhenean Sea     <b>Tyn</b><br>
		</p>
		<p>
			Variant Author: Don Hessong<br>
			jDip Variant Creator: Stefano Costantini<br>
		</p>
		]]>
		</DESCRIPTION> 
	
		<MAP adjacencyURI="ancientmed_adjacency.xml">
			<MAP_GRAPHIC ref="ancientmed" default="true" />
		</MAP>

		<!-- this is the default, but it's here just as an example -->
		<RULEOPTIONS>
			<RULEOPTION name="OPTION_BUILDS" value="VALUE_BUILDS_HOME_ONLY" />
		</RULEOPTIONS>
		<POWER name="Rome" active="true" adjective="Roman" /> 
		<POWER name="Carthage" active="true" adjective="Carthagenian" /> 
		<POWER name="Greece" active="true" adjective="Greecian" /> 
		<POWER name="Persia" active="true" adjective="Persian" /> 
		<POWER name="Egypt" active="true" adjective="Egyptian" /> 
		<STARTINGTIME turn="Spring, 1, Movement" />
		<VICTORYCONDITIONS>
			<WINNING_SUPPLY_CENTERS value="18" />
			<YEARS_WITHOUT_SC_CAPTURE value="7" />
			<GAME_LENGTH value="35" />
		</VICTORYCONDITIONS>
 	 	<!-- supply centers -->
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="ale" homepower="egypt" owner="egypt"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="ant" homepower="persia" owner="persia"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="ath" homepower="greece" owner="greece"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="bal" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="byz" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="car" homepower="carthage" owner="carthage"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="che" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="cir" homepower="carthage" owner="carthage"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="cre" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="cyp" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="cyr" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="dal" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="dam" homepower="persia" owner="persia"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="jer" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="lep" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="mac" homepower="greece" owner="greece"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="mas" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="mem" homepower="egypt" owner="egypt"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="mil" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="nea" homepower="rome" owner="rome"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="num" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="pet" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="rav" homepower="rome" owner="rome"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="rom" homepower="rome" owner="rome"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="sag" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="sad" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="sic" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="sid" homepower="persia" owner="persia"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="sip" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="spa" homepower="greece" owner="greece"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="tha" homepower="carthage" owner="carthage"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="the" homepower="egypt" owner="egypt"/>
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="tye" />
		<SUPPLYCENTER province="vin" />
		<!-- unit placement -->
		<INITIALSTATE province="ale" power="egypt" unit="fleet" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="ant" power="persia" unit="army" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="ath" power="greece" unit="army" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="car" power="carthage" unit="army" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="cir" power="carthage" unit="army" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="dam" power="persia" unit="army" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="mac" power="greece" unit="army" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="mem" power="egypt" unit="army" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="nea" power="rome" unit="fleet" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="rav" power="rome" unit="army" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="rom" power="rome" unit="army" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="sid" power="persia" unit="fleet" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="spa" power="greece" unit="fleet" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="tha" power="carthage" unit="fleet" />
		<INITIALSTATE province="the" power="egypt" unit="army" />
	</VARIANT>
</VARIANTS>